greetings everyone
it is uh October 21st 2022.
we're in textbook group number 50.1 no I
just have a slight typo
in my OBS it's cohort 2 and meeting
eight
we're discussing chapter four in our
first discussion of chapter four
we're going to
as we did not have any chapter or for
specific questions from cohort two today
largely we're going to be reviewing and
revising
questions that were initially addressed
in cohort one
taking a second pass and seeing where we
can like add some context and simple or
complex or however questions that we can
add so you can be adding in the chat
or in the questions tables directly or
like just unmuting and um
addressing them
so that we can have high quality and
quantity
of a large diversity of questions on the
material
that people are curious about when
they're reviewing the text
before we go to the questions table does
anyone have any general thoughts or
comments on chapter four
yes please Ollie
as we discussed in the previous cohort
this chapter is probably the most
technical one
in the whole book so
uh as people go through the formalism
here in this chapter uh I think it's
quite normal to not fully understand
every single equation there so uh in
case uh there are some difficulties in
getting uh in getting the content of
this chapter I think some of these
difficulties not all of them would be
unpacked in the later chapters
thank you very much totally agreed
anyone else want to make a general
chapter 4 comment
yeah there's such an interesting
rhythm
chapter one
being largely contextualizing and
framing
the chapter 2 3 dialectic
the low road and the high road
chapter four with a focus on the
generative model
and it is a very technical chapter
five
whiplashing over to neurobiology
and less on the fundamental formalisms
more on the neuroviological
relationships
that constitutes the epistemic first
half of the book
the second half of the book has kind of
a rhyming pattern
but less focused on epistemic and more
on pragmatic although the pragma of
epistem
whereas chapter 6
is focusing more on the recipe
for making the model and less of the
contextualizing then there's another
chapter pair
seven and eight discrete and continuous
time
and then chapter nine which is where
we're heading into in just um 50 minutes
in the first cohort with model based
data analysis and then chapter 10 as
sort of like the symmetry of chapter one
and the three appendices
okay
if anyone has comments of course just
like raise your hand
or speak up or put it in the chat or
however
all
on upvote these so we can upload them
when we've gone through them today
okay
well
let's scroll through the chapter before
we go to the questions just to get a
view of it
this chapter complements the preceding
chapters conceptual treatment of active
with a more formal treatment
it sets out the relationship between
free energy Bayesian inference form of
generative models and the Dynamics
obtained from minimizing free energy the
key focus is on how time is represented
4.2 Bayesian inference to free energy
equation four one recalls Bayes theorem
figure four one describes Jensen
inequality
which is related to the tonicity of the
natural log or just the logarithm
function in general
and it's uh pretty fundamental
point
and it speaks to the advantage of using
for example log probabilities
and the different kinds of operations
that are possible on logged values
here is an application of Jensen's
inequality
to derive a free energy value
as a bounded
um
is it bounding
foreign
ments amongst Bayes theorem and free
energy
generative models
to calculate the free energy we need
three things data a family of
variational distributions and a
generative Model comprising A prior and
likelihood
the section has two types of generative
model
the first is dealing with categorical
variables the second deals with
continuous variables
bigger 4.2
is helping gain some familiarity
with like nodes and edges
in a Bayesian graph
so here in a base graph
nodes are variables circular nodes are
variables
and edges which are like labeled with
the with a box
reflect their relationships
so
one can imagine and we'll return to this
in the questions
these map onto situations where like
there's a hidden cause and an
observation you know temperature in the
room
thermometer reading
two things that influence one outcome
one hidden thing that influences two
outcomes
a hierarchical model where something
changes something that results in an
outcome and so on
and then the boxes are labeled according
to the way that we might see that in a
more
uh
formulaic conditional likelihood
expression
vertical line means conditional upon
so like
box too is the probability distribution
of Y conditioned upon X
because of the directedness of this
error
figure 4 3 is a very central figure in
the textbook
and it
sets up the similarities and differences
largely
between the discrete time and the
continuous time formulations of active
inference generative models in terms of
partially observable Markov decision
processes through discrete time
and for the um more uh Taylor series
expansion-like approach used for
continuous time
does anyone want to like give a thought
or an overview on what is happening in
figure four three
yes Ali and then anyone else
well the top figure is
um what happens when we
uh uh when we want to model uh discrete
time uh discrete Time Event and the
bottom one is more
conducive to modeling The Continuous
time phenomena so as we see you see
they're quite parallel and
the only difference or at least the most
important difference here is the role
that policies play in the discrete time
case and the V play and the continuous
time case and the policy is denoted with
the pi and the top figure and it relates
to the top figure relates to the Palm DP
approach to modeling the discrete time
phenomena as we'll see at length in
chapter seven and the bottom one is
unpacked in more I mean in chapter 8 I
guess
excellent
again anyone can uh raise their hand and
go for it but just to kind of
describe what the nodes and edges are
here we'll be thinking about like the
temperature in the room is the hidden
State and the thermometer is the
observation
so in the discrete time formulation this
is the temperature in the room
through time it's the hidden State it's
in the generative process
then there's an a matrix
here labeled as 2 which is the
distribution of observations on the
thermometer conditioned upon the
temperature at that time
so the a matrix can be used as a
recognition density to do inference on
the hidden State given the observation
or it can be used in a generative
capacity
given a temperature to emit
distributions of thermometer
observations
the 3 corresponds to the B Matrix
which is the distribution of the state
at the next time conditioned upon the
state at the given time and the policy
pie
so 3 or B
escribes how the temperature is changing
Through Time
so this kind of through line of hidden
State and then a b Matrix or three and
then a hidden State this is something
changing through time and then Pi is
policy which is uh a function of the
decision making of the entity
and it influences how States change
their time that's the discrete time
formulation time Point negative one zero
and one
or however and
often you see a d or a prior which is uh
how the first hidden State value gets
initialized
that's the discrete time formulation
in the continuous time formulation
they're being laid out side by side
because the isomorphy of the models
is apparent they have the same
topological structure
however there are some really important
differences
rather than describing
how a hidden State changes through time
at explicitly demarcated time points
like
minute 12 minute 13 minute 14.
um what's Happening Here
is that
the the value of the Hidden State at the
focal time is still in an a matrix
relationship with observables so the
probability of Y given X
is exactly analogous to this one
of the observations conditioned on the
hidden state
however taking the place of the B Matrix
three above here which describes how
hidden States change their time in the
discrete time formulation
is actually a edge that describes the
derivative of x
conditioned upon X and V
which relates to slowly changing causes
in the world analogous to policy
and so this is actually not doing
explicit prediction of future explicit
time points
but rather it's doing something like a
Taylor series expansion
where as you take more and more
derivatives further and further away
from a focal point
you gain better and better approximation
through Power series expansion
from a focal point
using higher and higher derivatives
so here's like an example
here's a sine wave
and the first derivative
just gives you this locally linearizable
range
but there's a well-defined computational
complexity for a Taylor series
you can say the zeroth order is just
zero in the first order just a linear
regression
and then there's just a quadratic and
then there's just a third power
relationship and so on and so as you get
more and more
getting into the blue and the purple and
so on
you get better and better fit and you
extend the range of fit further and
further out
and it always gets strictly better
this is going to come back in chapter
seven and eight which are going to focus
more directly on the discrete and
continuous time formulations
but for here and four
they're just being introduced as
different ways that we can have a
generative model in active
so now figure four or section four four
is gonna
come to the top of four three
there's some formalisms related to
categorical distributions that are
compatible with partially observable
Markov decision processes
here's an expected free energy G
that describes some different
partitionings
on as a function of policies
evaluating policies based upon their
impact on the pomdp
four key ingredients for the discrete
time generative model
a b c d
then moving to continuous time
but first there is a kind of a technical
interlude
on Markov blankets previously there was
a box defining the markout blanket and
here it's discussed in the context of
message passing yes GSF anywhere if you
want to call attention to
yeah
[Music]
um I was going back to the figure four
three
so in looking at the at the parallel
between the top and the bottom figure so
in the in the top figure Pi that is the
policy
is obviously something that is selected
by the agent right
what about new in the like I mean
the the Greek letter that that is uh
that is paralleled to Pi in the bottom
figure
uh new is it um because he said slowly
slowly varying causes in in the
environment or something like that but
is that something emitted or selected by
the agent or is it something because
yeah
does anyone have a thought on this the
distinction is just between discrete and
continuous is not between like something
that that it's a autonomous autonomously
selected by the agent or something that
is you know happening in the environment
right
huh Ali
uh actually in continuous
um in continuous time situation uh the
new here can also be
um
related to uh the non-cognitive aspects
of the system such as the attractors of
the system so that's why it's described
in terms of the slowly varying causes
for instance in chapter 8 we will see
that uh well we have some static
variables According to which the system
behaves so that's not exactly something
that the system will choose per se
it's some some
some variables or some states towards
which the system that will approach so
that's yeah that's why uh they've termed
it in battery so for instance when
applying to to movements
that can be some sort of
um
anatomical constraint of the movement
something like that
exactly yeah I see okay thank you
yeah
thank you for um
sharing that Ali
it reminds me of the question
that
came later
action is part of in this is chapter
eight action is part of the generative
process not the generative model
and so the actual
um
interpretation of slowly varying causes
and the mapping of slowly varying causes
to real world phenomena
is
one
interesting
area
another
General point
is that uh if we look to the figures
we'll see that the first figure
is the action perception
Loop
and initially
there's some usage of the base graph
in terms of elaboration on the action
perception Loop
and so on
but when we get to chapter four and the
generative model
we don't see the action perception Loop
represented the same way
and so it's an interesting question to
ask
where these variables
map onto for example The Entity model
this isn't simply an entity model
okay so it's completing our our quick
scan before we go to the questions
message passing and Mark all blankets
this is definitely an area that we could
um
learn a lot more
about
and this is also an area where software
packages exist
with the work of the bias lab
and therefore knee
package
okay
figure four four Bayesian message
passing
does anyone want to describe this figure
Just one thought well the overall
thought is is this supposed to be
something that we're supposed to in
detail
understand
or is it more like an illustrative
representation
I was thinking exactly the same when I
saw it it's like here's the kind of food
you could make or is this like here's
how you make this one dish
um there are uh
also it's not red from left to right per
se
at the level of the figure the caption
begins with a right
so starting with the left the scheme
could be expanded hierarchically
collapsing over time steps and policies
for Simplicity so just looking at the
left one
here the subscripts have I
on the bottom then the subscripts have I
plus one
but you see the same squiggle Pi s
Epsilon
so this is showing that within the
context of a hierarchical model
you can have recurring patterns
of topological relationships of a base
graph
to enable for example hierarchical
predictive processing active
Bayesian action selection Etc models
and then that is collapsed over time
steps and policies
so what's happening here
so this is going to be unpacking within
one layer
on the right side
and we see like so here there's no
superscript but we can just take that to
be like Pi I so this is going to be this
quartet
being expanded out so here's o tilde
like o Through Time coming in
and here's like the actual discrete time
observations coming in
here's Epsilon
and S
in a um
uh predictive processing capacity
and these are illustrating with labeled
edges some of them
the relationships
between these different variables
squiggle in this case
that's funny when you search for this
wiggle it finds this the it finds the
other Sigma as well
squiggle sub Pi t
is not two natural logs being
subtracted a natural log subtracting
another natural log so what happens when
you subtract what's log a minus log B
it's the same as log a divided by B log
open parenthesis a divided by B
so this is Computing a ratio
between
the observation and the preference
if that is one
then
the incoming observations are exactly
the preferences
the preference distribution
if there's a surplus then the
observation is higher
if there's a deficit below one then it
means that it's lower
I hope that is
correct way to say it
um
so here's message passing and
relationships amongst variables
and we we see that kind of like
with an Epsilon intermediating
we see the S relating to the O at a
given time so this is a lot like the a
matrix
and here's the role of policy
now we're in the um continuous time 4.5
Ali please
I think this figure can be usefully
compared with figure
7.12 because uh I believe uh the figure
we'll see in chapter 7
7.12 I guess yes that's it is the
uh I mean hierarchy the other
interpretation of this uh figure from
chapter four uh in terms of its uh
hierarchical relationships but uh from
graphical probabilistic modeling point
of view and the other thing is uh that
uh I mean the final position Sigma uh I
don't think it's defined explicitly in
the uh text but
it's been defined as the expected
prediction error in the actor in The
step-by-step tutorial paper so uh yes
that's also
I wanted to
mention that definition as well
thank you
this step-by-step tutorial
which is also a four-part model stream
is very very useful
in some ways it is almost textbook
length
whereas in chapter four
there was first the general discussion
of Bayes graphs like again
one cause one observation one cause two
observations two to one one to one to
one
and then
instantly into the juxtaposition between
discrete and continuous time
as we've looked through today
in contrast the approach taken in step
by step first off is to only focus on
the discrete time formulation
but then they walk through a sequence
of graphs
and connect them to like increasing
levels of complexity building towards
the one that we see in 4.3
it's a little later than one might
expect in the paper
sorry about that here it is
starting
with just
a simple graph
that is exactly analogous
to the one on the top left
so they start with a static perception
then
in the step by step
they introduced this kind of e motif
by showing a prior and three time points
two changes observations mediated by the
a
this is corresponding to the music
listening example
so it's going to come up later in the
textbook
then policy
as a way to influence state transition
matrixes is introduced on the top right
and free energy as an objective function
Guided by preferences
to do policy selection as inference
and then finally on the bottom right
there is some Precision on policies
which is just a bringing in another
variable beta and gamma which have like
a inverse relationship to each other
so that you can talk about like
um
High precision
as
low ambiguity and vice versa
so it's different
ordering of talking about generative
models okay
we're in the continuous time
branch
I'm just copying a link that Ali sent
because I I just sorry I just wanted to
mention that uh The Continuous time
counter counter part 4 that's
step-by-step paper might be this one
from uh 2017 by Rafael bogach because in
this paper uh it almost exclusively
deals with the continuous time active in
prints
great
generalized coordinates motion
this is again bringing back this idea of
the Taylor series if this block line is
the function that has to be approximated
if you only have one parameter to
approximate it and you want to do it at
this line your first
is just the actual value of the function
at T equals zero
Tau equals zero then the first
derivative
value at the time x of o
and the first derivative
then
the adding in the second derivative
and so on so as you add more and more
and more derivatives you'll get better
and better approximation to arbitrary
functions
and you'll get that with a totally known
form
that can be represented in a vector
as the generalized coordinates of motion
and in physics
it's it's
um used in engineering it's used in PID
control this has come up in many live
streams and discussions
because you can say whatever function
I'm approximating
I want the first five derivatives
and then you know that your data
structure is only going to have five
coefficients for example
and they've joked
many times like six generalized
coordinates are sufficient
six layers of the brain
cortex regions
though in some ways that's kind of
that makes it seem like the six layers
of the cortex are like this
but actually the cortical column is not
like little six floors where each one is
its own predictive Loop actually the
layers are connected differently
more
formalisms in the continuous time
setting
with
generalized coordinates of motion
tilde over a variable is representing
trajectories
one footnote is that this is still in
the um
date based
base of Bayesian mechanics
Ollie or anyone else please
correct if this is not the case so the
tilde here
is
a summary notation helping us represent
trajectories of states
which is moving us towards the path
formulation of Bayesian mechanics
but is not the same as a true path
formulation
hope that is fair to say
the LaPlace approximation
is this yes just help me please yeah so
in that in the till the formalism now
when we are talking about generalized
coordinates if we were talking about
standard coordinates uh X tilde would be
X still there would be X at time T
comma X at time t plus 1 x at time t
plus two Etc now in the generalized
coordinates the X tilde would be X comma
first derivative of x comma second
derivative of x is that correct
yes
so oh tilde
with just a location coordinate would be
either a list or a vector depending on
whether you want to you know think about
it in terms of like a list with comma or
in terms of like a vector going down
that time yeah yeah then with
generalized coordinates
it is a matrix
so just it it could be represented
differently but here let's just say that
we're going to be working with it as a
list like you said
[Music]
so in this case columns
correspond to the list above
those are the time points
rows going down
are the generalized coordinates of
motions
so for each time point one two three
four five we have a vector which is
describing the location the first
derivative the second derivative and so
on I see I see so there would be six
rows
mm-hmm cool if we had six generalized
coordinates of motion
and
um this is used and discussed in um
live stream 26
particularly
and several other places
generalized coordinates
um
are like
they're kind of a uh a little not not
like a a trick or anything to get
Dynamics into a static representation
like if you just take a picture of a car
you can't tell if it's moving or not
but if you said this is a generalized
picture of a car
it's at
um it's at 12 on the number line
and its velocity is 10 this way
and its acceleration it's slowing down
and it's going to the right and the way
that it's slowing down is speeding up
then you can start to say a lot more
about the next steps of the car
exactly and that is representable in a
static
um snapshot
Ollie
uh and another way to looking at uh the
generalized coordinates is to see it as
a a dimensional reduction technique
because uh when we want to describe as a
very simple case
a trajectory in a Cartesian coordinates
uh well uh we'll definitely need at
least
um for example in a two-dimensional
trajectory we'll need two Dimensions but
if we look at it from a generalized
coordinates perspective we can just put
it into the Riemann manifold and
jettison one of the dimensions which
encapsulates that trajectory through a
specific time so one of the dimensions
would be reduced and then we can just
look at it trajectory directly look at
the behavior of the trajectory directly
from the consecutive derivatives we take
so that's a dimension reduction
technique as well
nice point
yeah when you said uh
you said on the remaining Romanian ring
onion manifold he said
can you
yeah yeah
because in the uh Punk array or Romanian
manifold uh we're dealing with uh not
exactly the Cartesian coordinates but uh
it's just the state space
defined as these kind of General
generalized coordinates
so it is already a
one dimension reduced coordinate so to
speak so that's the whole point behind
uh this I mean encompassing the state
space in that Romanian manifold not in
the Cartesian coordinates
because Cartesian coordinates need some
global coordinates to define the states
of the space but in generalized
coordinates it's more like a kind of
localized uh coordinates not Global ones
boom
yes this is a very well I don't know I
don't know much about the Romanian or or
the point manifold so yes I have some
readings to to do to understand that but
yeah this is very
deep and Powerful
um analytical Insight one other way to
think about generalized coordinates as a
dimensionality reduction technique from
a more computational applied perspective
is
if you want five coordinates of motion
you know exactly the size of that data
object if you say I'm going to consider
20 time points and five generalized
coordinates of motion you know exactly
the shape of that parameter or that
variable
now whether that captures whether that
manifold
or Subspace captures 10 or 90 or 100
percent of the variance
in the original space
is situational
but
um you will capture some variants
just like every principal component
analysis will capture some variance
in the space
and whether it captures enough is
situational
but
you know you get some and you know that
you've reduced the dimensionality to a
well-defined amount
which in many cases is essential
versus having like an unbounded number
of of unbounded size
um the motor reflex case has been
especially studied from The Continuous
time perspective
that's going to come up in the second
half of the book it comes up in a lot of
different other cases and in chapter
five
motor reflexes
box fortree describes the LaPlace
approximation
oh
there's no again as frequently that last
names don't really reduce uncertainty
about what something is talking about
much of the time
and so there'd be ways to describe some
of these things that wouldn't rely as
much on specific last names because
there's like a many-to-many mapping
between the technique and different last
names and so on and
um but just working with what we have
LaPlace approximation
is a quadratic approximator
that is an expansion around the mode of
a distribution
so the procedure for generating a
laplacian approximation is you find the
mode of a distribution which is the
tallest point on the distribution
then
an upside down Parabola is like fit to
that mode
the tip of the parabola is going to be
the the mode
of the distribution
the width of the parabola is going to
reflect a second parameter a variance
parameter
that captures as much as possible
of the original distribution
um
so this is kind of like
created if um a good thing about LaPlace
approximation is that no matter what
shape the original distribution has
you know your LaPlace approximation is
only going to need two parameters
the mode and the variants and so in that
way it's a lot like a gaussian
approximator although the gaussian
function is different than the quadratic
approximator
um they're similar because they both are
um have two parameters
the location of the midpoint and how
wide the function should be stretched
so
for empirical distributions which might
not fit cleanly to any specific
analytical family
this can be very helpful
because again you know that some density
of the target distribution will be
captured
now if you're dealing with like a super
tricky distribution where there's four
humps
all of very similar height
then the LaPlace approximation is going
to get tricked because it's only going
to capture like at best 25 percent of
the variance and it's gonna you're gonna
be very much um like unaware of these
other three big Peaks
however four distributions that have a
central tendency
broadly speaking the LaPlace
approximation does extremely well
some of these subtleties between like
LaPlace approximation variational Bays
and non-parametric bootstrap based
sampling techniques are explored in the
SPM textbook especially
all of this
was still inferential
but not action including
and that is very analogous to the
approach taken in the paper discussed in
uh live stream 43
which is on predictive processing itself
predictive coding a theoretical
experimental review
in this one eighty percent or something
in the paper is about hierarchical
predictive processing architectures and
then they go all right now we're just
going to slip in action
and it turns out to play very well
here we see a figure that's kind of
resonant with this one
we have a discrete time formulation here
we know that because we see like an
explicit time variable and like a time
minus one and time plus one
so that's how one knows that they're
dealing with a discrete time formulation
even if the variables were like called
different things
um in contrast
we see
a hierarchical architecture again
but
everything has been transposed into the
notation of the continuous time
where we saw like
why
coming in
whereas we saw
o coming in here
and that was
what we saw in four three o coming in to
discrete time y coming into continuous
time
so this figure four six is like related
to the previous message passing figure
and then there's a summary
so
chapter four as Ali mentioned at the
beginning
is
relatively technical
there's a lot of
techniques and notation
and forays into more General topics
ranging from Jensen's inequality at the
beginning of the chapter to generalize
coordinates of motion message passing in
the context of Markov blankets
evidence lower bound and free energy
calculations
and all of that is being done
in this side-by-side way
between discrete and continuous time
and that is um
broadly what chapter four
describes all of that is being done
because we're exploring
generative models in active inference
okay in our final minutes what are some
thoughts or ideas that people have that
we can come to next week
uh Yvonne
I'm past now
what does it mean to understand chapter
four what are we looking to get out of
chapter four
foreign
the discrete and continuous time
distinction is like
in my opinion the essence of of what is
in chapter four
um but I would like to like understand
more about the message passing because I
don't really get it all the way
um
as I would also love to like pick apart
and understand the the larger paper on
message passing by Kristen and some
colleagues that I don't remember
um
yeah yeah
but for me the greatest challenge is
that you know even though you you're
beginning to to grasp the theoretical uh
details the the moving from there to
actually implementing something is
is still uh still quite difficult
um and uh
you know Freestone says a quartz a lot
of time fine man saying you can only
understand when you start when you can
do it
uh but still it's uh that passage in
active inference is uh is still quite uh
challenging for me I mean
even after after having read the whole
book and you know and a few of the other
papers
uh so this is the
even though you know you you understand
this this for chapter four which is a
lot of the theory but still going from
there to implementing a model it's a
not easy I don't know if there's
something that uh affects everybody it
does
affect me for sure
well
certainly it does it's the fractal state
of play
at this moment that's why people aren't
just like blasting out active models
because there's like a lot of uh trails
to blaze
and also just as always compare it with
a linear regression you could read a 100
500 10 000 page textbook on linear
regression
and then you would sit down in front of
your programming language and you may
not specifically know how to quote apply
linear regression
linear regression has had a hundred
years of empirically focused development
on data input output visualization
training model adequacy model selection
there are just whole areas of Applied
statistics
women haven't turned their attention to
this area which is why we're doing it
so the most ancient comparator is linear
regression then to get one step closer
to seeing what the theory practice
synthesis looks like the SPM textbook
documentation and literature help us see
what it could look like and then
it'll have aspects of both of those and
some novelties
all right
very well thank you all for this fun
meeting thank you see you next week
thank you bye-bye